The last time I heard my son's voice
كانت آخر مرة سمعت فيها صوت ابني
was when he walked out the front door
عند خروجه من باب المنزل
on his way to school.
في طريقه إلى المدرسة.
He called out one word in the darkness:
نطق بكلمةٍ واحدةٍ في الظلمة:
"Bye."
"إلى اللقاء".
It was April 20, 1999.
كان ذلك في العشرين من أبريل، عام 1999.
Later that morning, at Columbine High School,
لاحقًا في ذلك الصباح في مدرسة كولومباين الثانوية،
my son Dylan and his friend Eric
قام ابني "ديلان" وصاحبه "أريك"
killed 12 students and a teacher
بقتل اثني عشرة طالبًا وأحد المدرسين
and wounded more than 20 others before taking their own lives.
وإصابة أكثر من عشرين بجروحٍ قبيل انتحارهما.
Thirteen innocent people were killed,
قُتِل ثلاثة عشر من الأبرياء،
leaving their loved ones in a state of grief and trauma.
تاركين مُحبينهم في حالةٍ من الحزن والأسى.
Others sustained injuries,
تكبّد غيرهم بإصابات
some resulting in disfigurement and permanent disability.
أدت بعضها إلى تشوهٍ وإعاقاتٍ مستديمة.
But the enormity of the tragedy
لكن فداحة هذه المأساة
can't be measured only by the number of deaths and injuries that took place.
لا يمكن قياسها وفقًا لعدد الموتى والإصابات التي حدثت فحسب.
There's no way to quantify the psychological damage
لا يمكن تحديد مدى الضرر النفسي
of those who were in the school,
لهؤلاء الذين تواجدوا في المدرسة،
or who took part in rescue or cleanup efforts.
وأولئك الذين شاركوا في أعمال الإغاثة والتنظيف.
There's no way to assess the magnitude of a tragedy like Columbine,
من الصعب جدًا تحديد حجم مأساة مثل كولومباين،
especially when it can be a blueprint
خاصة عندما يكون ذلك بمثابة مخطط
for other shooters who go on to commit atrocities of their own.
لغيرهم من مطلقي النار الذين يمضون في اقتراف وحشيتهم.
Columbine was a tidal wave,
كانت حادثة "كولومباين" موجة عاتية،
and when the crash ended,
وحالما انتهت هذه الصدمة،
it would take years for the community and for society
فقد يتطلب ذلك سنين بالنسبة للمحيط والمجتمع
to comprehend its impact.
ليتمكنوا من إدراك تأثيرها.
It has taken me years to try to accept my son's legacy.
انقضى من عمري سنين طويلة لتقبل ما أورثه لي ابني.
The cruel behavior that defined the end of his life
السلوك الوحشي الذي حدّد نهاية حياة ابني
showed me that he was a completely different person from the one I knew.
أظهر لي بأنه كان مختلفًا تمامًا عن الشخص الذي أعرفه.
Afterwards people asked,
سألني الناس بعدها:
"How could you not know?
"كيف لكِ ألا تعرفي ذلك؟"
What kind of a mother were you?"
"أي أمٍّ كنتِ؟"
I still ask myself those same questions.
لا زلتُ أسأل نفسي هذه الأسئلة ذاتها.
Before the shootings, I thought of myself as a good mom.
قبل الحادثة كنت أظن بأنني أمُ جيدة
Helping my children become caring,
مساعدة أبنائي ليصبحوا حذرين
healthy, responsible adults
ذوي صحة جيدة، وبالغين يتحملون المسؤولية،
was the most important role of my life.
كانت أهم دور في حياتي.
But the tragedy convinced me that I failed as a parent,
لكن المأساة جعلتني أثق بأنني فاشلة كـأم،
and it's partially this sense of failure that brings me here today.
وهذا الشعور بالفشل هو أحد الأسباب التي جاءت بي هنا اليوم.
Aside from his father,
إلى جانب والده،
I was the one person who knew and loved Dylan the most.
فقد كنت الشخص الذي عرف "ديلان" وأحبه كثيرًا.
If anyone could have known what was happening,
إن كان أي شخص بمقدوره أن يعرف ما سيحدث،
it should have been me, right?
فهو أنا، أليس كذلك؟
But I didn't know.
ولكنني لم أعرف.
Today, I'm here to share the experience
أنا هنا اليوم لكي أشارك تجربتي
of what it's like to be the mother of someone who kills and hurts.
لما يعني أن تكوني أمًّا لشخص يقتل ويُسيء.
For years after the tragedy, I combed through memories,
لعدة سنين بعد المأساة تعمقت خلال الذكريات،
trying to figure out exactly where I failed as a parent.
محاولةً تحديد الجانب الذي فشلت به كوالدة.
But there are no simple answers.
ولكن لا يوجد أجوبة بسيطة.
I can't give you any solutions.
لا يمكنني إعطاؤكم حلولًا.
All I can do
كل الذي أستطيع فعله
is share what I have learned.
هو مشاركتكم ما تعلمته.
When I talk to people who didn't know me before the shootings,
عندما تحدثت مع الناس الذين لم يكونوا يعرفوني قبل إطلاق النار،
I have three challenges to meet.
كان لدي ثلاثة تحديات للتعامل معها.
First, when I walk into a room like this,
الأول، عندما أدخل إلى قاعة كهذه،
I never know if someone there has experienced loss
لم أعرف مطلقًا ما إذا كان هناك شخص ما قد فقد عزيزًا
because of what my son did.
بسبب ما فعله ابني.
I feel a need to acknowledge the suffering caused by a member of my family
أشعر بالحاجة إلى الاعتراف بالمعاناة التي سببها أحد أفراد أسرتي،
who isn't here to do it for himself.
والذي لا يتواجد هنا لكي يفعلها بنفسه.
So first, with all of my heart,
لذلك أولًا، من كل قلبي،
I'm sorry if my son has caused you pain.
أعتذر إذا سبّب ابني لكم الألم.
The second challenge I have
التحدي الثاني لدي
is that I must ask for understanding and even compassion
أنه يجب علي أن أطلب التفهّم وكذلك الرحمة
when I talk about my son's death as a suicide.
عندما أتحدث عن وفاة ابني انتحارًا.
Two years before he died,
قبل عامين من وفاته،
he wrote on a piece of paper in a notebook
كان قد كتب على ورقة في المفكرة
that he was cutting himself.
أنه كان يقطع نفسه.
He said that he was in agony
قال بأنه كان في صراع عنيف مع النفس
and wanted to get a gun so he could end his life.
وأراد أن يحصل على سلاح ناري حتى يتمكن من إنهاء حياته.
I didn't know about any of this until months after his death.
لم أكن على علم بأي من هذا حتى أشهر بعد وفاته.
When I talk about his death as a suicide,
عندما أتحدث عن وفاته انتحارًا،
I'm not trying to downplay the viciousness he showed at the end of his life.
لا أحاول أن أقلل من الإثم الذي ارتكبه في نهاية حياته.
I'm trying to understand
أنا أحاول أن أفهم
how his suicidal thinking
كيف أن تفكيره بالانتحار
led to murder.
قاده إلى الجريمة.
After a lot of reading and talking with experts,
بعد الكثير من الدراسة والنقاش مع المختصين،
I have come to believe
وصلت إلى الاعتقاد
that his involvement in the shootings was rooted not in his desire to kill
بأن تورطه في إطلاق النار لا يعود إلى رغبته في القتل،
but in his desire to die.
بل إلى رغبته في الموت.
The third challenge I have when I talk about my son's murder-suicide
التحدي الثالث لدي عندما أتحدث عن جريمة ابني وانتحاره
is that I'm talking about mental health --
هو أنني أتحدث حول الصحة النفسية --
excuse me --
عفوًا --
is that I'm talking about mental health,
هو أنني أتحدث حول الصحة النفسية،
or brain health, as I prefer to call it, because it's more concrete.
أو الصحة العقلية، كما أفضِّل أن أسميها، لأنها أكثر واقعية.
And in the same breath, I'm talking about violence.
وفي نفس الوقت، أنا أتحدث عن العنف.
The last thing I want to do is to contribute to the misunderstanding
آخر شيء أرغب في فعله هو أن أساهم في الفهم الخاطئ
that already exists around mental illness.
الموجود مسبقًا عن المرض العقلي.
Only a very small percent of those who have a mental illness
نسبة قليلة فقط ممن لديهم مرض عقلي
are violent toward other people,
يكونوا عنيفين تجاه الآخرين،
but of those who die by suicide,
ولكن من بين الذين يموتون بالانتحار،
it's estimated that about 75 to maybe more than 90 percent
يقدّر بأن حوالي 75% أو ربما أكثر من 90%
have a diagnosable mental health condition of some kind.
يعانون من مشاكل عقلية يمكن تشخيصها.
As you all know very well,
كما تعرفون جيدًا،
our mental health care system is not equipped to help everyone,
نظام الرعاية الصحية العقلية ليس مجهزًا لمساعدة الجميع،
and not everyone with destructive thoughts
وليس الجميع ممن لديهم أفكار مدمرة
fits the criteria
يتناسب مع المعايير
for a specific diagnosis.
لتشخيص محدد.
Many who have ongoing feelings
العديد ممن لديهم مشاعر مستمرة
of fear or anger or hopelessness
من الخوف أو الغضب أو اليأس
are never assessed or treated.
لا يتم تقييمهم أو معالجتهم.
Too often, they get our attention only if they reach a behavioral crisis.
وكثيرًا ما لا يحصلون على اهتمامنا إلا إذا وصلوا إلى أزمة سلوكية.
If estimates are correct
إذا كانت التقديرات صحيحة
that about one to two percent of all suicides
أن حوالي 1 - 2% من جميع حالات الانتحار
involves the murder of another person,
ترتبط بقتل شخص آخر،
when suicide rates rise, as they are rising for some populations,
وعندما ترتفع معدلات الانتحار،
the murder-suicide rates will rise as well.
فإن معدلات القتل والانتحار ستزداد كذلك.
I wanted to understand what was going on in Dylan's mind prior to his death,
أردت أن أستوعب ما كان يحدث في عقل "ديلان" قبل وفاته،
so I looked for answers from other survivors of suicide loss.
لذلك بحثت عن الإجابات من الناجين الآخرين من مأساة الانتحار.
I did research and volunteered to help with fund-raising events,
بحثت وتطوعت في فعاليات جمع التبرعات،
and whenever I could,
وكلما استطعت،
I talked with those who had survived their own suicidal crisis
تحدثت مع أولئك الذين نجوا من الأزمة الانتحارية الخاصة بهم
or attempt.
أو الذين حاولوا.
One of the most helpful conversations I had
إحدى أكثر المحادثات المفيدة التي أجريتها
was with a coworker
كانت مع زميلة لي في العمل
who overheard me talking to someone else
سمعتني بالصدفة أتحدث مع شخص آخر
in my office cubicle.
في مقصورة مكتبي.
She heard me say that Dylan could not have loved me
سمعتني أقول بأن "ديلان" لم يستطع أن يحبني
if he could do something as horrible as he did.
إذا كان قد استطاع أن يفعل شيئًا فظيعًا كالذي فعله.
Later, when she found me alone,
لاحقًا، عندما وجدتني لوحدي،
she apologized for overhearing that conversation,
اعتذرت عن سماع المحادثة بالصدفة،
but told me that I was wrong.
وأخبرتني بأنني كنت مخطئة.
She said that when she was a young, single mother
قالت لي بأنها عندما كانت أمًا عزباء شابة
with three small children,
مع ثلاثة أطفال،
she became severely depressed and was hospitalized to keep her safe.
أصيبت بالاكتئاب الشديد وتم نقلها إلى المستشفى للحفاظ على سلامتها.
At the time, she was certain
في ذلك الوقت، كانت واثقة
that her children would be better off if she died,
بأن حال أطفالها ستكون أفضل إذا ماتت،
so she had made a plan to end her life.
فوضعت خطة لكي تُنهي حياتها.
She assured me that a mother's love was the strongest bond on Earth,
وأكّدت لي أن حب الأم هو أقوى رابطة على الأرض،
and that she loved her children more than anything in the world,
وأنها قد أحبت أطفالها أكثر من أي شيء في العالم،
but because of her illness,
ولكن بسبب مرضها،
she was sure that they would be better off without her.
كانت على يقين من أنهم سيكونون أفضل حالًا بدونها.
What she said and what I've learned from others
ما قالته وما تعلمته من الآخرين
is that we do not make the so-called decision or choice
هو أننا لا نصنع ما يسمى القرار أو الاختيار
to die by suicide
للموت عن طريق الانتحار
in the same way that we choose what car to drive
بنفس الطريقة التي نختار فيها نوع السيارة لقيادتها
or where to go on a Saturday night.
أو إلى أين سنذهب في ليلة السبت.
When someone is in an extremely suicidal state,
عندما يكون شخص ما في قمة الرغبة بالانتحار،
they are in a stage four medical health emergency.
فهم في المرحلة الرابعة التي تحتاج إلى رعاية صحية طارئة.
Their thinking is impaired and they've lost access to tools of self-governance.
تفكيرهم تدهور وفقدوا إمكانية الوصول لأدوات التحكم بالذات.
Even though they can make a plan and act with logic,
على الرغم من استطاعتهم وضع خطة والتصرف بمنطقية،
their sense of truth is distorted by a filter of pain
إلا أن إداركهم للحقيقة انحرف بواسطة مُرشِّح الألم،
through which they interpret their reality.
والذي من خلاله يفسرون واقعهم.
Some people can be very good at hiding this state,
بعض الأشخاص بإمكانهم أن يكونوا جيدين جدًا في إخفاء هذه الحالة،
and they often have good reasons for doing that.
وغالبًا ما يكون لديهم أسباب وجيهة للقيام بذلك.
Many of us have suicidal thoughts at some point,
كثير منا لديهم أفكار انتحارية في مرحلة ما،
but persistent, ongoing thoughts of suicide
لكن الأفكار المستمرة والمتواصلة بالانتحار
and devising a means to die
وابتكار الوسائل للموت
are symptoms of pathology,
هي أعراض المرض،
and like many illnesses,
ومثل العديد من الأمراض،
the condition has to be recognized and treated
يجب التعرف على هذه الحالة ومعالجتها
before a life is lost.
قبل خسارة حياة شخص ما.
But my son's death was not purely a suicide.
لكن وفاة ابني لم تكن مجرد انتحار.
It involved mass murder.
فقد شملت القتل الجماعي.
I wanted to know how his suicidal thinking became homicidal.
أردت أن أعرف كيف أصبح تفكيره الانتحاري هو القتل.
But research is sparse and there are no simple answers.
لكن الأبحاث ضئيلة ولا توجد إجابات بسيطة.
Yes, he probably had ongoing depression.
صحيح، ربما كان لديه اكتئاب مستمر.
He had a personality that was perfectionistic and self-reliant,
كانت لديه شخصية متكاملة، كما كان يعتمد على ذاته،
and that made him less likely to seek help from others.
مما قلّل من احتمالية طلبه المساعدة من الآخرين.
He had experienced triggering events at the school
لقد مرّ ابني بأحداث محفزة في المدرسة
that left him feeling debased and humiliated and mad.
جعلته يشعر بالإهانة والخزي والعصبية.
And he had a complicated friendship
كان لديه علاقة صداقة معقدة
with a boy who shared his feelings of rage and alienation,
مع ذلك الصبي الذي شاركه مشاعر الغضب والاختلال،
and who was seriously disturbed,
والذي كان يشعر جديًا بالاضطراب،
controlling and homicidal.
الميل للسيطرة والقتل.
And on top of this period in his life
وفي أوج هذه الفترة من حياته
of extreme vulnerability and fragility,
ذات الضعف الشديد والحساسية المفرطة،
Dylan found access to guns
وجد "ديلان" السبيل للأسلحة
even though we'd never owned any in our home.
على الرغم من عدم حيازتنا لأي منها في المنزل.
It was appallingly easy for a 17-year-old boy to buy guns,
كان سهلًا بشكل مروع لفتى بعمر السابعة عشر أن يقوم بشراء أسلحة
both legally and illegally, without my permission or knowledge.
سواء بشكل قانوني أو غير قانوني، دون إذني أو معرفتي.
And somehow, 17 years and many school shootings later,
وبطريقة ما، 17 عامًا والعديد من المدارس تعرضت لإطلاق النار لاحقًا،
it's still appallingly easy.
ما زال سهلًا بشكل مفزع.
What Dylan did that day broke my heart,
ما فعله "ديلان" ذلك اليوم كسر قلبي،
and as trauma so often does,
وكما تفعل الصدمة غالبًا،
it took a toll on my body and on my mind.
كان له أثر كبير على جسدي وعلى ذهني.
Two years after the shootings, I got breast cancer,
بعد عامين من إطلاق النار، أصِبتُ بسرطان الصدر،
and two years after that, I began to have mental health problems.
و بعد عامين بعد ذلك، بدأت أعاني من مشاكل في الصحة العقلية.
On top of the constant, perpetual grief
وبشكل ثابت تمامًا، الحزن الدائم؛
I was terrified that I would run into a family member
كنت مذعورة من التواصل مع أي من أفراد العائلة لأحد ضحايا "ديلان"،
or be accosted by the press
أو مخاطبتي من قبل الصحافة
or by an angry citizen.
أو من أحد المواطنين الغاضبين.
I was afraid to turn on the news,
كنت خائفة من مشاهدة الأخبار،
afraid to hear myself being called a terrible parent or a disgusting person.
خائفة أن أسمع نفسي قد لُقبتُ بالأم الفظيعة أو الشخص المثير للاشمئزاز.
I started having panic attacks.
بدأت أتعرض لنوبات ذُعر.
The first bout started four years after the shootings,
بدأت النوبة الأولى بعد أربع سنوات من إطلاق النار،
when I was getting ready for the depositions
عندما أصبحت مستعدة للادعاءات
and would have to meet the victims' families face to face.
وكان يتعين علي مقابلة عائلات الضحايا وجهًا لوجه.
The second round started six years after the shootings,
الجولة الثانية بدأت بعد ست سنوات من إطلاق النار،
when I was preparing to speak publicly about murder-suicide
عندما كنت أستعد للتحدث علنًا عن القتل والانتحار
for the first time at a conference.
للمرة الأولى في أحد المؤتمرات.
Both episodes lasted several weeks.
استمرت كلا الحلقتين عدة أسابيع.
The attacks happened everywhere:
حدثت النوبات في كل مكان:
in the hardware store, in my office,
في متجر أجهزة الحاسوب، في مكتبي،
or even while reading a book in bed.
وحتى عندما أقرأ كتابًا في السرير.
My mind would suddenly lock into this spinning cycle of terror
كان عقلي يُغلق فجأة في خضم موجة الذعر المتكررة هذه،
and no matter how I hard I tried
ومهما كنت أحاول بجدية
to calm myself down or reason my way out of it,
لتهدئة نفسي أو الاستماع لصوت عقلي بعيدًا عن ذلك،
I couldn't do it.
لم أستطع فعل ذلك.
It felt as if my brain was trying to kill me,
كان شعورًا و كأن دماغي يحاول قتلي،
and then, being afraid of being afraid
ومن ثم، فإن خوفي من أكون خائفة
consumed all of my thoughts.
استنفذ كل أفكاري.
That's when I learned firsthand
هذا عندما أدركت مباشرةً
what it feels like to have a malfunctioning mind,
ما يمكن أن تشعر به عندما يصيبك عطل في العقل.
and that's when I truly became a brain health advocate.
وهذا عندما أصبحت حقًا المدافع عن صحة الدماغ.
With therapy and medication and self-care,
مع العلاج والأدوية والرعاية الذاتية،
life eventually returned
عادت الحياة أخيرًا
to whatever could be thought of as normal under the circumstances.
إلى ما يمكن اعتباره طبيعيًا في ظل هذه الظروف.
When I looked back on all that had happened,
عندما نظرت إلى ما كان قد حدث سابقًا،
I could see that my son's spiral into dysfunction
أستطيع أن أرى دوامة أبني خلال الخلل الوظيفي
probably occurred over a period of about two years,
ربما حصلت على مدى عامين تقريبًا،
plenty of time to get him help,
الكثير من الوقت لكي يحصل على المساعدة،
if only someone had known that he needed help
إذا كان شخص ما فقط قد عرف أنه يحتاج إلى مساعدة
and known what to do.
وعرف ما يمكن القيام به.
Every time someone asks me,
في كل مرة يسألني فيها شخص ما،
"How could you not have known?",
"كيف لم تكوني تعرفين؟"،
it feels like a punch in the gut.
يبدو هذا السؤال وكأنه لكمة في الأحشاء.
It carries accusation and taps into my feelings of guilt
إنه يحمل الاتهامات ويلامس أعماق شعوري بالذنب
that no matter how much therapy I've had
حتى أنني على الرغم من كمية العلاجات التي خضعت لها
I will never fully eradicate.
لم أستطع القضاء عليها نهائيًا.
But here's something I've learned:
ولكن هناك شيء قد تعلمته:
if love were enough
إذا كان الحب كافيًا
to stop someone who is suicidal
لإيقاف شخص ما يفكر بالانتحار
from hurting themselves,
من إيذاء نفسه،
suicides would hardly ever happen.
الانتحار بالكاد سوف يحدث.
But love is not enough,
ولكن الحب لا يكفي،
and suicide is prevalent.
والانتحار هو السائد.
It's the second leading cause of death
هو السبب الثاني المسبب للموت
for people age 10 to 34,
للأشخاص الذين تتراوح أعمارهم بين 10- 34،
and 15 percent of American youth
و15% من الشباب الأمريكي
report having made a suicide plan
تقول التقارير أنهم وضعوا خطة للانتحار
in the last year.
في العام الماضي.
I've learned that no matter how much we want to believe we can,
لقد تعلمت أنه لا يهم مدى إيماننا بأننا نستطيع،
we cannot know or control
لا نستطيع أن نعرف أو نسيطر
everything our loved ones think and feel,
على كل شيء يفكر به أحبابنا ويشعرون به،
and the stubborn belief that we are somehow different,
والاعتقاد المتجذر بأننا مختلفين بطريقة ما،
that someone we love would never think of hurting themselves
بأن شخصًا ما نحبه لا يمكن أن يفكر أبدًا في إيذاء نفسه
or someone else,
أو أي أحد آخر،
can cause us to miss
يمكن أن يقودنا إلى أن نفوّت
what's hidden in plain sight.
ما هو مخفي بعيدًا عن الأنظار.
And if worst case scenarios do come to pass,
وإذا كانت أسوأ السيناريوهات وأردنا أن نتجاوزها،
we'll have to learn to forgive ourselves for not knowing
سيتوجب علينا أن نتعلم مسامحة أنفسنا لعدم المعرفة،
or for not asking the right questions
أو لعدم سؤالنا للسؤال الصحيح
or not finding the right treatment.
أو عدم عثورنا على المعالجة الصحيحة.
We should always assume
يجب علينا أن نفترض دائمًا
that someone we love may be suffering,
بأن شخصًا ما نحبه ربما قد يعاني،
regardless of what they say
بغض النظر عما يقولون
or how they act.
أو كيف يتصرفون.
We should listen with our whole being,
يجب علينا أن نسمع بكل كينونتنا،
without judgments,
دون أحكام،
and without offering solutions.
بدون تقديم حلول.
I know that I will live with this tragedy,
أنا أعلم أنني سأعيش مع هذه المأساة،
with these multiple tragedies,
مع هذه المآسي المتعددة،
for the rest of my life.
في ما تبقى من حياتي.
I know that in the minds of many,
وأنا أعلم أنه في عقول الكثيرين،
what I lost can't compare to what the other families lost.
أن ما فقدته لا يمكن مقارنته مع ما فقدته العائلات الأخرى.
I know my struggle doesn't make theirs any easier.
أعلم أن كفاحي لا يمكنه تخفيف ذلك أبدًا.
I know there are even some who think I don't have the right to any pain,
أعلم بأنه يوجد البعض ممن يعتقدون أنه ليس لي الحق بأن أتألم،
but only to a life of permanent penance.
ولكن فقط إلى حياة من التكفير الدائم عن الذنب.
In the end what I know comes down to this:
في النهاية ما أعرفه يخلص إلى هذا:
the tragic fact is that even the most vigilant and responsible of us
الحقيقة المأساوية أنه حتى أكثر الناس الحذرين والمسؤولين منا
may not be able to help,
ربما لا يستطيع تقديم المساعدة،
but for love's sake,
ولكن من أجل الحب،
we must never stop trying
يجب علينا ألا نتوقف أبدًا عن المحاولة
to know the unknowable.
لمعرفة ما يستحيل معرفته.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)